我父亲为了我的大好前途
My father dissolves our marriage
解除了我们的婚约
in favor of more promising opportunity.
我们之间什么都没有了吗
Is there nothing left between us?
只有回忆了
Memories only.
竞技场已被烧为灰烬
The arena is burned to fucking ground.
顺带着送了不少罗马人上西天
With many Romans among the ashes!
还有救吗
Can he be healed?
他的伤势恐怕无力回天
This man is beyond what would warrant life.
他是奥诺玛默斯 可不是寻常人
His name is Oenomaus and he is more than common man.
又在竞技场里找到一百来具尸体
A hundred more bodies pulled from the arena.
废墟里还有这个东西
This was found in the wreckage.
诸神如此惩罚我 让我的父亲死于非命
The gods have punished me by striking down my father.
- 这样还不够 - 盖尤斯
- It is not enough. - Gaius?
要不是你腹中的孩子
The only reason you have not joined your father
你早就去九泉下和你父亲团聚了
is the child that grows within you.
打杂的奴隶不可能成为角斗士
House slaves will never be gladiators.
而我们缺的正是能打仗的人
We need fighting men.
也许该重新考虑那不勒斯的计划了
Perhaps it is time to revisit plans towards Neapolis.
目标是运送战俘的奴隶商船
And its slaver ships from foreign wars.
你要攻打港口
You would attack the port?
《斯巴达克斯：复仇》
《圣誓》
我他妈的真讨厌这鬼天气
I do not care for the fucking rain.
更讨厌有人三更半夜打搅我休息
Nor disturbance at unreasonable hour.
我会尽快让你忘掉这些烦心事的
I would have you quickly removed from such concerns.
我可以付一大笔钱
And well compensated for allowing eyes
只是看看你的货
upon your latest offerings,
不想等到拍卖会
in advance of auction…
这么晚了还冒雨过来
You must have pressing need,
想必你有急事吧
to venture out on such a night.
要是等天亮恐怕就来不及了
I fear the rising sun would dash hopes of it being met.
要得急 价格就高
Short of time, long of coin.
你想要什么样的奴隶
What form of slave narrows your purpose?
能打仗的最好
I have a desire towards fighting men.
角斗士
Ah, gladiators!
罗马的很多冠军都是我送去的
I've supplied Rome with many of its' finest champions.
可惜卡普亚的竞技场不在了
Sadly with the arena in Capua gone,
对这些奴隶的需求也一落千丈
there's less interest in these men of such talents.
对我而言再好不过了
Fortunate for my cause then.
来吧
Come.
看看有没有我中意的
Let us see how you can further aid it.
请原谅这股臭味
Forgive the stench.
莱茵河东岸的这帮蛮子就喜欢屎尿味
Savages east of the Rhine tend to favor their own shit.
我本想先把他们擦擦
I intended to have them scraped
抹点油 再送去拍卖
and oiled before auction,
不过估计也于事无补
but I feared that would do little to improve
他们天生这么臭
their natural odor.
这些女人怎么样
And how do you find the women?
跟男的一个德行
As unpleasant as their men.
我劝你还是别操她们为好…
I would not recommend lustful hand placed upon…
你受的苦到此为止了 兄弟
你懂我们的语言
我跟你们是老乡
做好准备 我救你们出去
那个大胡子畜生也能听懂
杀了他 杀了他
钥匙拿来 快点
Keys, quickly.
放他们出来
Release them.
你手下人挺厉害
他们不是我手下
斯巴达克斯是头儿
你不是我们那里来的
You not from our lands.
但我也被罗马人的锁链捆过 跟你们一样
Yet I was once bound in chains by the Romans, as you were.
我可不会轻易放过他们
A grievance I would see them pay dearly for.
杀罗马人
光想想我就兴奋
他说他们愿意跟我们走
He says they are with us.
走吧 兄弟们
离开这条破船
真是幸运啊
A fortunate thing.
这一船人都是你的老乡
That we liberate a ship filled with your people.
是诸神保佑
The gods favor us.
我们再也不用
No longer will we have to listen
看那帮高卢人的眼色了
to those fucking Gauls again.
走吧 兄弟们
Geht Bruder.
蒙卡图对你是赞赏有加
Good Mercato spoke highly of you.
可惜他再也不能
A grave misfortune that his tongue
开口说话了
has forevebeen silenced.
正是因为他的逝去 我才会到这里来
His passing cause for my presence before you.
逝去
Passing?
这词儿根本无法体现他死得有多惨
Too gentle a word for how he was ushered from this life.
他想逃离斯巴达克斯的怒火
Blood and brains staining the pulvinus
结果脑子肠子流了一地
as he thought to flee Spartacus' wrath.
斯巴达克斯的怒火殃及了很多无辜的人
A thing that threatens to consume many innocent lives.
我们还以为你也死翘翘了
We had thought you were mangled corpse,
埋在支离破碎的竞技场废墟里面
the sundered beams of the arena your tomb.
那天发生的事让我有点精神恍惚
The events of the day caused me absent proper mind.
不过现在没事了
It has since returned.
你也回到城里了
And you to our streets.
我说过 蒙卡图是我的雇主
Mercato my purpose, as I said.
我去竞技场帮忙
There is the matter of coin,
还没拿到报酬呢
for services tended upon the sands.
你的任务是干掉那些
You were secured to execute those shits
追随斯巴达克斯的畜生
that follow Spartacus.
问题是你一个人也没杀
I do not recall any falling to your sword.
要是斯巴达克斯没来
It would have been happened
我肯定能杀了他们
had Spartacus not appeared.
那样你要的报酬也就能兑现了
And coin would have materialized the same.
木已成舟 我也无能为力
Yet the past cannot be altered.
我现在缺钱 行政官
I am without coin, Magistrate.
不然我也不会回来
I would not have returned otherwise.
看在你多年在竞技场娱乐大家的份上
For your years of pleasing the crowd in the arena.
现在请跟那伟大的竞技场一起
Now follow once noble monument,
在我面前消失吧
and collapse from sight.
不好意思 行政官
Magistrate? Apologies,
竞技场坍塌时 我的鲁迪斯也不见了
my rudis was lost when the arena fell.
- 没有它… - 不要得寸进尺
- Without it… - You press beyond reason!
厄运已经降临卡普亚
I'll winds has blown Capua
破坏了这里的正常生活
from once steady course.
有事就去找民政官葛雷博
Take further matter to Praetor Glaber.
说不定他心情好
Perhaps you can entice coin from him as well,
能赏你几个钱
if caught upon proper mood.
带来不幸
…and misfortune.
我们都失去了至爱的亲人
We have all suffered loss of those closest to us.
包括我们伟大共和国的元老
Even a senator of our great Republic,
我妻子的父亲
a man my wife called father,
也不幸丧命在
has been ripped from this world
斯巴达克斯那帮杂种的手下
by Spartacus and his mongrel hordes.
如今我们敬爱的赛普修斯
And now beloved Seppius
也在这场叛乱中离我们而去
has fallen to this festering disease of rebellion.
他的奴隶杀害了他
Murdered by his own slaves,
并偷偷逃走
who even now spirited themselves away
加入斯巴达克斯的叛军
to join Spartacus against us.
危难关头 我们必须提高警惕
We must be ever vigilant in these dark times.
绝不放过任何可疑迹象
We must bring to light even dimmest shadow
及早扼杀叛乱的苗头
of betrayal if it is revealed to us.
从今往后
From this day forward,
任何敢提到斯巴达克斯这个名字的奴隶
any slave who dares to whisper the name Spartacus
都要被处以极刑
shall be put to death.
包括那些
Even those
罗马民政官的奴隶
owned by a praetor of Rome.
抓住她
Seize her.
主人
Dominus!
我什么都没做
I did nothing!
主人
Dominus!
别跟他对着来
Do not speak against him.
听听她是如何求饶的
Listen how she begs!
昨天她这张嘴
Pleading with the very tongue
还在歌颂斯巴达克斯
that only yesterday had praise for Spartacus upon it!
歌颂那些杀掉赛普修斯的奴隶
Praise for the slaves that murdered Seppius!
幸亏我忠诚的妻子无意间听到了
Praise most fortunate to be overheard by loyal wife.
主人
Domina…
是真的
It is true.
我听到她说了
I hear her speak it.
杀她一次根本不够
Would that she had more than one life to take.
我们就以此警告所有
Let this serve as warning to any slave
密谋叛乱的奴隶们
who would conspire against us.
抱歉
Apologies
没必要
None deserved.
刚才的打法太傻了
It was a foolish attempt.
你想直接砍掉对方的脑袋
You seek to part head from shoulders.
其实杀人有很多简单的方法
There are blows that kill with less effort.
那我就要学会
Then I shall learn them.
他不愿离开她一步
He is never from her side.
斯巴达克斯要他去那不勒斯
Spartacus wanted him towards Neapolis,
但他执意要陪着她
but he would not leave her.
也许让他和艾力冈分开才是最好的
Though perhaps it's best to keep him and Agron parted.
妮维雅好幸运 有人这么爱她
Naevia is blessed to be loved so deeply.
你也是 斯巴达克斯深爱着你
As are you, by Spartacus.
克雷斯
Crixus!
我以前教你攻不忘守
I taught you never to lower guard.
现在你要这样教妮维雅了
Now see Naevia to same instruction.
奥诺玛默斯
Oenomaus.
我以为再也见不到你了
I thought you for the afterlife.
我也是
As I you.
可我们都受了很重的伤
Yet we did not escaped deep wounds.
一定要让罗马人千倍奉还
A thing to be visited upon the Romans a thousand fold.
尤其是奥诺玛默斯来到我们这边了
Now that Oenomaus stands with us once again.
我那时太傻 没有跟你们走
He was a fool to be gone so long from your side.
过去的都过去了
Such things are of the past.
我们展望未来吧
Let us turn thought towards future.
看看未来有多美好
And what joys it may hold.
来 让我们互相拥抱 互称兄弟
你完成了不可能完成的任务
You've done the impossible.
我们应该举杯庆祝
我们只有水
最好不过了
赛杜鲁斯清醒时是猛兽 喝醉了就是傻瓜
小纳美特斯人说得太他妈对了
队伍扩大了
Our ranks swell.
我们需要更多武器
We will need more weapons.
这个问题一定要解决
A concern that must be addressed.
还有更严重的问题
I sense a deeper one.
这些都是艾力冈的族人
These are all fucking Agron's people.
仅一天我们的人就多了一倍
Our forces have doubled in a single day.
而且都是能打能杀的人
With people who are no stranger to battle and blood.
他们听谁的
And who will they follow?
我这次发现你的屁股稍稍动了动
I detected a hint of movement in your hips this time.
我抽插的时候
A subtle thrust
你迎合了
as I bore down.
开始喜欢我操你的感觉了吗
You begin to enjoy my cock inside of you?
回答我
I would have answer.
是的
Yes.
是
Yes…
什么
what?
是的 主人
Yes, Dominus.
谁听过如此美妙的声音
Has a man ever heard so sweet a sound?
你的声音
Your voice…
你的爱抚
your touch…
热乎乎的大腿
the warmth of your thighs…
难怪昆图斯拜倒在你的裙下
Is it a wonder Quintus fell beneath your spell?
毫无保留地宠爱你 送你东西
Lavishing you with affection and gifts.
你现在改叫我主人了
You call me dominus now, in his place.
作为回报 我要送你一件礼物
It is only just that I present you with something in return.
你哪里弄来这么多东西
How did you come by such bounty?
别人白送的
They were freely given.
死人不需要这些东西了
By the dead who no longer have need for them.
等这个箱子装满了
When this chest is full,
它将见证我阿舒尔更上一层楼
it's worth shall see Ashur to even greater heights.
不过
Yet
给你的东西
for one such as you…
我是拿钱买来的
something purchased with coin…
我知道昆图斯痴迷于发色
I know how fond Quintus was of the color.
我要你戴上
I would have you wear it.
当我看着你站在阳台上时
So that I may look up to you upon the balcony…
就知道你是我的女人
and know that you are mine…
我知道你心如刀割
Heart has been deeply wounded.
如果有什么能安抚你
If there is anything to offer as balm,
尽管说出来
you need but voice it.
他的人由你指挥了吗
You take command of his men?
是的
I do.
要是他当初同意跟你合作就好了
Would that he had given them freely in life.
就没有斯巴达克斯什么事了
Spartacus would be a distant memory.
我哥哥就不会死
And my brother yet by my side.
如果是这样就好了
If only it had been so.
我父亲也不会死
My father would yet grace this world.
我的奴隶也不会因此被钉死在十字架上
And my slave would have had no cause to be crucified.
你哥哥的手下来了
Your brother's men arrive.
走
Come.
一起检阅他们
Let us review them,
让他们发誓效忠于我
and bind them to cause with oath of loyalty.
站好了
Fall to attention!
不要说话
Hold tongue…
听好了
and give attention!
谁代表你们发言
Who stands forth as your voice?
奥克塔维斯•塔苏斯
Octavius Tarsus.
我代表他们发言
I stand for them.
你们的雇主被暴徒斯巴达克斯夺去了性命
Your benefactor has been ripped from this world by the villain Spartacus.
由于他已过世
Towards his end,
我征召你及你的兄弟
I conscript you and your men
到盖尤斯•克罗迪斯•葛雷博麾下
into the army of Gaius Claudius Glaber.
宣读圣誓 效忠于我
Recite the Sacramentum, and commit loyalty.
我 奥克塔维斯•塔苏斯
I, Octavius Tarsus,
以神圣而伟大的朱庇特之名发誓
swear by Jupiter Optimus Maximus,
我等当维护并捍卫共和国和平
that I shall uphold and defend the Republic.
她的敌人就是我等的敌人
I swear to have her enemies as my enemies
她的朋友亦是我等的朋友
and her friends as my friends.
你换回以前的发色了
You've taken to your old color.
感觉不适合就换了
I fear it no longer suits me.
一切言行举止都为了她的荣誉
… her honor in all my thoughts, words, and actions.
我发誓将身体和生命献给共和国及其军队
I pledge my body and life to the Republic and to its army
接受民政官盖尤斯•克罗迪斯•葛雷博领导
under the leadership of Praetor Gaius Claudius Glaber.
人够了吗
Will they be enough?
加上我的军队 够了
Added to my own troops, yes.
足够将斯巴达克斯绳之以法了
They will be enough to bring Spartacus to justice.
我不是要他伏法
I do not seek justice.
我是要复仇
I seek vengeance.
他怎么杀我哥哥 我就要他怎么死
The man who took the life of my brother must die the same.
血债血偿
In blood and slaughter.
以神圣而伟大的朱庇特之名 我发誓
By Jupiter Optimus Maximus, I so swear.
以神圣而伟大的朱庇特之名 我们发誓
By Jupiter Optimus Maximus, we so swear.
去外面扎营吧
Set camp outside these walls.
你们由萨尔维斯指挥
Salvius will see you to orders.
并且干掉斯巴达克斯
And the death of Spartacus.
感谢你的一片心意
Gratitude for your kindness.
我可是特别珍惜呢
Know that I have treasured it.
或许你以后住在这里比较好
Perhaps it would be best if you made home here.
就在我们家
Beneath our roof.
我本打算明早就去我在庞贝的叔叔家
I leave in the morning for my uncle's villa in Pompeii.
我可不允许你在斯巴达叛党
I would not have you upon the road
仍阴魂不散时冒险出行
while the threat of Spartacus still remains.
我会给你叔叔捎个口信
I will send word to your uncle,
如果你对我的提议还满意的话
if you find solace in the thought.
非常欢迎你的到来
Your presence offers great comfort.
能和你们同住是我的幸运
I am blessed to find myself among you.
来吧
Come.
我来给你安排一下
Let us make arrangements.
就在不久前 我还以为他懦弱无能
Was it so recent that I thought him weak?
现在我每次看他的眼睛就不寒而栗
I now gaze into his eyes and tremble
他眼里藏着可怕的东西
at what lurks behind them.
你千万不要沉浸在这种情绪里
Do not work yourself into an unfortunate state.
你怀的孩子
Your child
是我活着的唯一原因
Is the only reason I yet live.
我根本取悦不了他
Nothing I do pleases him.
他为了先前的事情惩罚我
He tortures me for what I have done.
戴莎拉受了刑
Thessala crucified.
现在又邀请赛皮娅进家住
Seppia invited into our house.
他看她的那种眼神…
The way he looks at her…
如果只能是这样的命运
I would see myself over cliff,
我宁愿跳下悬崖
if this is all fate now holds.
那我的心就全碎了
My heart would follow to the rocks below.
我不能这样活下去了
I cannot live like this.
我也是
Nor I.
最后一点肉了
The last of our meat.
我都忘了我的族人有多大胃口了
I forgot how much my kin devour upon a sitting.
最近你好像忘了不少事
Much seems to have slipped mind of late.
你派我去那不勒斯侦查
You sent me to scout Neapolis
报告港口的动向
and report on opportunity.
所以搞定了那艘船
Their ship provided it.
当时还有没有别的船只呢
Were there any others that may have afforded the same?
还有两艘
Two.
一艘来自大马士革
One from Damascus.
另一艘来自高卢
The other Gaullia.
这些情况你应该告诉我
News I would have cared to know.
大马士革的人都不中用
Men from Damascus are of low quality
而且不可信
and even lower trust.
那高卢人呢
And Gaullia?
我不希望身边充斥着高卢人
I would not have these ranks filled with Gauls.
- 克雷斯… - 是值得尊敬的人
- Crixus - Is an honorable man.
明早我带你那些兄弟们去打猎
I will take your brothers to hunt when day breaks,
补充食物
to replenish supply.
顺便考察我们是否合得来
And gauge how we might come together.
让他们能说通用语就说通用语
Tell those who are able to speak in common tongue.
这样我们都能知道他们的想法
So all among us may know their thoughts.
他们肯定大有作为
They will prove great asset.
我保证
I give you my word.
傻逼
Cunt.
居然想吃霸王餐
Nothing's free.
我听说你死了
I heard you were dead.
跟那些在竞技场倒塌时死去的人
Carried to the afterlife with all the others
一起上了黄泉路
that fell beneath the arena.
我还活着呢
I yet breathe.
不过我的钱袋是完蛋了
My purse however has suffered fatal blow.
没钱让你张开大腿了
I have no coin to pry open thighs.
只要我愿意 不出钱也行啊
They may yet widen, of their own accord.
不赚钱的事儿
A miracle lacking profit.
你和你主人很少做啊
For you and your master.
你还记得当时受奴役的感觉吗
Do you recall what it was like to have one?
在获得自由之前
Before you gained your freedom?
没人是真正自由的
No man is ever truly free.
除了斯巴达克斯
Except for Spartacus.
和追随他的人
And those who follow him.
他攻打竞技场的时候你看见他了吗
Did you see him when he attacked the arena?
他是什么样的人
What form of man was he?
你说话当心点
You speak of dangerous things.
不光我谈论他
I'm not the only one.
我们很多人都在说
There's talk among many of us
希望能跟他走
towards joining his cause.
有什么前途呢
There is no cause…
无非就是带领一帮无辜的傻瓜送死
Only the leading of innocent fools to their death.
你没有钱是吧
You have no coin then?
只有离开这个破地方的盘缠钱
A few denarii for passage away from this fucking city.
别想斯巴达克斯的事情了
Strike Spartacus from your thoughts,
跟我走吧
and come with me…
这不是强大的甘尼克斯吗
The mighty Gannicus.
看到你还活着
It is joyous occasion,
真让人喜出望外呀
to find you yet alive.
膝上还有美女相伴
With ripe offering perched upon lap.
抱歉
Apologies.
打搅男欢女爱之事实在不妥
It is unforgivable to come between man and cunt,
不过我必须跟我兄弟说几句话
yet I must have words with my brother.
好一个可人的尤物啊
An enticing creature.
当然你从不缺女人投怀送抱
Of course you never lacked the attention of fine women.
有话快说 有屁快放
If you seek words, break them and be done.
这么多年了 你嘴巴还是不太干净啊
The years have not seen you to better manners.
你的同伴还是这种货色
Nor you to better company.
不要乱说话
I would advise caution.
这些人现在是
These men are the hand of
盖尤斯•克罗迪斯•葛雷博的左膀右臂
Praetor Gaius Claudius Glaber.
那你呢
And what are you?
他的老屌还是屁眼
His cock or his ass?
我是他的意志
I am his will.
其实就是负责治安嘛
Bound by duty to restore order.
把小姑娘钉在十字架上吗
By nailing little girls to the cross?
任何谈及斯巴达克斯及其叛乱的奴隶
Any slaves who whispers of Spartacus and his rebellion…
都跟那姑娘一个下场
shall find place beside her.
我对这些言论没兴趣
I have no interest in whispers.
对民政官的意志也没兴趣
Nor the will of your praetor.
大胆狂言
Bold words.
对于奴隶而言
From a slave.
你别搞错了
You mistake me.
我可是自由人
I am a free man.
是 你华丽变身为竞技场之神时
Yes, I was there upon the sands
我站在沙场上亲眼目睹那一幕
when you became a god of the arena!
那场面让人永生难忘
It was a sight never to be forgotten!
甘尼克斯 在开幕式的骁将之战中
Gannicus, besting twenty gladiators
击败了二十名角斗士
in the primus of the opening day!
而奖赏呢
And his reward?
就是鲁迪斯
The rudis!
一把刻着他辉煌胜利的木剑
A wooden sword carved with the legend of his victories!
自由的证明 顺应万众的呼声
Proof of freedom, demanded by adoring crowd!
给他们瞧瞧啊
Show them.
我敢说他们肯定非常期待
I am sure they would be eager
一睹这稀罕宝贝的风采
to lay eyes upon such rare marval.
不给看
No?
你没带在身上吗
You do not have it upon you?
你明知故问
You know I do not.
如同我知道民政官会非常乐意
As I know the praetor will be most pleased
有你鞍前马后地效劳
with the presence of your company…
我很惊讶地发现你还活在这世界上
I find it surprising that you are still of this world.
不过更惊讶的是
More so that you did not think it wise
你要拖到这么晚才现身
to present yourself at sooner convenience.
抱歉
Apologies.
甘尼克斯总是惜字如金
Gannicus has always been a man of few words.
据说他喜欢和行政官大人长篇大论
Yet he favor the Magistrate with whole sentences, I'm told.
我只不过想完成交易
I sought only to conclude business.
你的定位太低了
You aim too low.
斯巴达克斯把整个竞技场砸在你头上
Spartacus brings the arena down upon you,
你却站在这里毫发无伤
and yet here you stand.
如同凤凰浴火重生
A phoenix risen from its ashes.
他的确有诸神庇护
The gods have truly blessed him.
如今他的现身
As they now bless me,
是诸神对我的庇佑
with his presence.
当你走上竞技场时
I was moved by the reaction of the crowd,
观众的反应真让我震惊
when you stepped upon the sands.
他们声嘶力竭地喊出你的名字
The swell of their voices, heralding your name.
充满了期待
Filling the air with hope.
即使那场灾难造成了破损
Even tarnished by blood and calamity,
它的价值仍然存在
such a thing yet can hold value…
你的鲁迪斯
Your rudis.
要我拿什么换
And its price?
一句简单的誓言
A simple oath.
从今以后听从我的命令
Edging yourself to my command.
露迪雅曾经也是斯巴达克斯的受害者
Lucretia was also once thought victim of Spartacus.
如今是用来安抚情绪的
Yet now stands a powerful symbol,
强有力的象征
used to calm spreading concern.
我要让你跟她一样
I would add you as such.
一个曾属于巴蒂塔斯家的奴隶
A former slave of the House of Batiatus,
发誓要将叛逃的兄弟绳之于法
now sworn to bring errant brothers to justice.
这样的人似乎有一个了
It appears you already have one of those.
阿舒尔擅长见不得光的事情
Ashur's talents are of the shadows.
我要让你正大光明地登场
I would present you in glorious light
站在我的军队前面
at the front of my troops.
让民众再度热血沸腾地呼喊
To the roar of the crowd once again.
如果我对这种事情没兴趣了呢
And if I no longer crave for such a clamor?
你已经自由了
You're a free man.
你的命运由你自己掌握
Your fate is your own.
几天后我会再度邀请你
I will send for you again in a few days.
希望到时你能做出正确的决定
And expect reasonable decision to accompany you.
告退
Praetor.
原谅我 民政官大人
Forgive me, Praetor,
甘尼克斯并不可信
but Gannicus cannot be trusted.
当初对你的评价也一样
The same once said of you.
可你照样站在这儿
Yet here you stand.
派人跟着他
See one of your men to follow.
要是甘尼克斯意图离开卡普亚
If Gannicus attempts to leave Capua,
就把他钉死
crucify him.
没别的办法了吗
Is there no other way?
你对盖尤斯的看法是正确的
You were right about Gaius.
他不是那个只敢偷偷窥探的人了
The man he was no longer peers from behind his eyes.
他不会为言语或者柔情所动
He will not bewayed by words or gentle touch.
我们要逃脱只能付出血的代价
Only blood can set us free now.
露迪雅
Lucretia…
长痛不如短痛
It will hurt but for a moment.
把裙子掀起来
Lift your dress.
那不勒斯
Neapolis?
一艘运送奴隶的船遭到攻击
A slaver ship was set upon.
上面载着从莱茵河东岸抓来的俘虏
It carried prisoners captured east of the Rhine.
一群战士
Warriors.
成为斯巴达克斯的帮凶
To aid Spartacus' cause.
这很明显
An obvious conclusion.
派遣军队去那不勒斯
Dispatch men to Neapolis.
询问有没有人看到
Question anyone who may have seen
他们获救后逃向何方
where they were headed after liberation.
遵命
Praetor.
盖尤斯
Gaius…
快去找医师
Fetch the medicus.
快
Quickly!
伊莉西娅
Ilithyia!
她怎么了
What has happened to her?
奄奄一息的孩子
It is a sign from the gods.
带来了诸神的警示
One carried by the child yet to breath life.
警示什么
And its meaning?
再留在这座满是鲜血和恐惧的城里
Your heir will die if it remains in a city
你的继承人就会死去
cursed with blood and fear.
等她恢复我就送她去罗马
I will have her carried to Rome as soon as she's able.
在我过去之前 由我的贴身侍卫照看她
With trusted guard to watch over her at all times, until my return.
我应该同去 这样可以照顾她
I shall accompany her and tend to her needs.
容我插句话 大人
Apologies, Praetor.
露迪雅是夫人的闺蜜
Lucretia's a dear friend to your wife,
可也是卡普亚的定心丸
yet offers greater comfort to Capua.
如果她不能现身
I fear the people will fall to despair,
恐怕民众就绝望了
absent her divine presence.
明智的建议
Wise counsel.
明天你照例到集市去
Have your presence known tomorrow in the market.
安抚民心
Ease mind of our city,
让他们相信诸神站在我这边
and continue to assure them the gods favor my efforts.
我们一直在训练那些获救的人
We have been training those freed of bond.
不过我们没人当过教练
Yet none among us ever held title of Doctore.
我对战争和战士一无所知
I have no knowledge of soldiers and war.
我只懂训练角斗士的方法
I know only the ways of a gladiator.
接受角斗训练的军队最强大不过了
I can think of no fiercer army, so instructed.
给他们上一堂课 开开他们的眼界
Open their eyes as man can do giving a course.
正如你开了我的眼界
As you have opened mine.
我要和艾力冈他们去打猎
I hunt with Agron and his people,
好好考察他们
to better gauge them.
回来后我就帮你的忙
I will lend aid when I return.
恐怕你要一个人打猎了
I fear you hunt alone.
天没亮艾力冈就带着那些人走了
Agron left with the others before light broke.
艾力冈
Agron.
你明知道我的想法
You hunt without me,
居然没叫我就走了
when you knew my intention.
他们一大早就醒了
They woke before the sun,
迫不及待地要享受自由生活
and were eager to take advantage of freedom.
你跟娘们温存的时候 我们正忙着呢
说他们能懂的话
我们去打猎
We hunt.
找食物
Catch meat.
还有罗马人的酒
And Roman drink!
我从来不知道树林里还能找到酒
I did not know these forests were stocked with such.
你们怎么找到这个的
Where did you come by this?
是路上的一辆马车…
A wagon along the road
在离我们这么近的地方 连武器都没有
You attacked the road so close to our position?
你们就贸然出击
Absent proper weapons?
没人看到
No one see.
全杀光了
All dead.
我们准备开伙吧
让那些傻逼们瞧瞧
什么叫抽插自如
真后悔冒着生命危险救了这帮人
Glad I risked my life for this lot.
他们增强了我们的实力
They see us to prope force.
他们给我们增加了暴露的危险
They see us to nothing but discovery.
让罗马人放马过来
Let the Romans come.
我不想再做缩头乌龟了
I'm tired of hiding like frightened bbits.
我们还没有能力对抗正面攻击
We are not ready for a direct assault.
小孩子都看得出来
Something even a child could see.
是小孩还把你从竞技场救出来
This child helped save you from the arena.
给大家带来了这么多战士
And fills our numbers with warriors.
小畜生屁都没带来 只引来一群疯狗
The pup has found himself nothing but a pack of wild dogs.
反正绝对不会追随一个该死的高卢人
Ones that will never follow a fucking Gaul.
抱歉没叫你就出去了
Apologies for leaving without you.
我怀疑这孩子没什么诚意
I question that boy's sincerity.
我们跟新来的弟兄一起吃东西吧
Let us break meal with our new brothers.
再看能不能解决问题
And attempt to settle this.
愿诸神保佑你
May the gods bless you…
我们很多人都在说
There's talk among many of us
希望能跟他走
towards joining his cause.
你认识她吗
You knew her?
傻丫头
A foolish girl.
不该说的话还那么大声地讲
Who spoke too loudly of things she should not have.
城里到处都有人
The city is filled with ears
竖着耳朵偷听叛逆的言论
straining for whispers of betrayal.
同样有人在暗地监视
It is filled with eyes as well…
要是打算出城
Attempt to leave the city,
就跟你的朋友一个下场了
and share a cross beside your friend.
我不是你的奴隶
I am not your slave.
休想拿这种话威胁我
And I will not bow to your threats.
我也不愿意
Nor would I see you.
打什么谜语呢
The oracle of fucking riddles.
有话就直说
Come to plain words.
你站在葛雷博面前时
I saw something in your eyes,
我看透了你的想法
when you stood before Glaber.
你不光是在权衡他的提议
I saw something beyond a man weighing decision.
诸神赐予了你读心的能力了吗
The gods bless you with gift to see into my thoughts now, do they?
她这样的人只会更多
More like her will die.
不管有罪无罪
The guilty. The innocent.
夹在葛雷博的怒火
There will stand no difference
斯巴达克斯的复仇中间 根本没有区别
when caught between Glaber's wrath and Spartacus' vengeance.
你到底要我怎样
And what would you have me do?
接受提议
Take up offer
杀戮我曾经的兄弟们吗
and turn on those that I once called brother?
不
No.
我要你干掉盖尤斯•克罗迪斯•葛雷博
I would have you end the life of Gaius Claudius Glaber.
他一心想取斯巴达克斯的性命
He is desperate to claim Spartacus' life.
结果走火入魔 如今比色雷斯人还要危险
So consumed, that he now stands more threat than the Thracian himself.
杀了他又能怎样
And what difference would it make?
罗马很快就会派人来接替他
Rome would only send another to take his place.
斯巴达克斯是要葛雷博为他妻子的死负责
Spartacus blames Glaber for part in his wife's death.
只要葛雷博一死
Remove him from the world,
血债就还清了
and the scales of blood will be balanced.
斯巴达克斯就会离开罗马
Spartacus will drift from Rome.
无论哪边都不会再有人丧命
No more lives will be lost. On either side.
葛雷博的妻子
Glaber's own wife,
今晚就要前往罗马
this very night leaves for Rome.
为了护送她 葛雷博派出了一半的贴身侍卫
Taking with her half his personal guard to see her safely from the city.
至于看守宅子的那些守卫 我可以引开
I could distract any that remain posted to the villa entry,
到时候你就趁虚而入
giving opportunity for a single man
在葛雷博睡觉时取他性命
to take Glabe's life while he sleeps.
由斯巴达克斯来背黑锅
And Spartacus to receive the blame.
你疯了
You have lost mind.
这世界都乱成什么样儿了
The whole world has slipped from reason.
我只想恢复原样
I seek only to restore it.
避开阿舒尔的人
Rid yourself of Ashur's man.
等到月上梢头 我自会为你扫清障碍
When moon stands highest I will see path cleared.
答应我吧
Choose to set upon it.
否则无数人都要为此遭罪
Or see legions fall to pointless suffering.
扯掉他的鸡巴
你喝了酒 简直跟赛杜鲁斯一样野蛮
我可不输给男人
无论哪方面
你的族人真是给劲儿
Your people, they lift spirit.
不是所有人都这样想
Not all are so moved.
来玩玩吧 兄弟
但愿他们同归于尽
Perhaps they'll kill each other,
那才值得庆祝呢
and give proper cause for celebration.
你真是刻薄
You are an impossible man.
你知道我是什么样的人
Something thing you've always known.
睁只眼闭只眼算了
And chose to ignore.
不要总盯着人家的缺点
To better see the man beneath his faults…?
跟我一起唱 黑哥们
Sing with me, my dark brother!
玩玩我的女人
Share my woman.
我听不懂你的话
I know not your words.
卢戈教你
Lugo will teach!
奥诺玛默斯下不来台了
Oenomaus finds himself assaulted.
他们太喜欢闹了
They are a boisterous people.
有时候还是要喝点酒 犯点傻
Sometimes wine and foolishness are needed.
增进感情嘛
To forge stronger bond.
跟我唱啊
Sing with me!
现在可不是时候
Now is not the time for such things.
会有这种时候吗
Is it ever?
不会
No.
我去找卢戈要杯酒来喝
I will try and wrest a drink from Lugo for us to share.
顺便帮奥诺玛默斯解围
And in the act, aid Oenomaus in escape.
我想说服他同意你一起走
I tried to convince him to let you come.
但他就是不肯
He would not be moved.
无关紧要了
It is a thing of no matter.
你为我所做的一切…
What you have done for me…
真希望我们永远不要分开
Would that we were never parted.
我会再次回到你身边的
You shall find me again to your arms.
比你想象的还快
Sooner than expected.
我说服甘尼克斯来除掉盖尤斯
I sway Gannicus to forever remove Gaius from concern.
等他完事 我就大喊大叫
When it is done I will raise clamor,
确保甘尼克斯有来无回
and see Gannicus follow to the afterlife.
伊莉西娅
Ilithyia.
时候到了
It's time.
盖尤斯
Gaius
我会想念你
You shall be missed.
今晚怎能只喝水
酒
Wine.
给你喝
We share.
谢谢 但是克雷斯在等我
Gratitude, but Crixus awaits.
高卢人 没错
The Gaul, yes.
他的眼睛
I see his eyes.
盯着我
At me.
没好感
No love.
他需要时间
He needs time.
还有酒
And drink.
我会转告他
I'll tell him.
告诉他 我不喜欢他的眼睛
Tell him his eyes I not like.
你的还不错
Your eyes better…
让我过去
Let me pass.
老子要日破你这张漂亮的小脸蛋
赛杜鲁斯 住手
克雷斯
Crixus.
赛杜鲁斯
Sedullus.
全都冷静点
Calm yourselves!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus!
够了
Enough!
你们就是这种东西
Is this what you are?
畜生
Animals,
宰了你们才高兴
demanding slaughter?
我们给了你们自由
We give you freedom.
你们就干出这种无耻的事情来
And you repay it with blood and dishonor.
如果你们不能真心诚意地当我们的兄弟
If you can not stand among us as trusted brother
如果你们不遵守我的命令
if you can not follow my orders
现在就滚
take leave now.
否则跟赛杜鲁斯一个下场
Or join Sedullus in death.
我跟从斯巴达克斯
I follow Spartacus.
不愿意的人 我绝不拿他当族人
And call no man my kin that does not stand so.
杀掉赛杜鲁斯的人
The man that kills Sedullus
勇不可挡
is great warrior.
卢戈跟定你了
And Lugo follow.
民政官 有急事报告
Praetor, pressing concer.
甘尼克斯已经做出决定了
Gannicus has made his decision.